<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-lodderstedt-oauth-par-00" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="oauth-par">OAuth 2.0 Pushed Authorization Requests</title><seriesInfo value="draft-lodderstedt-oauth-par-00" stream="IETF" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="T." surname="Lodderstedt" fullname="Torsten Lodderstedt"><organization>yes.com</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>torsten@lodderstedt.net</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="B." surname="Campbell" fullname="Brian Campbell"><organization>Ping Identity</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>bcampbell@pingidentity.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="N." surname="Sakimura" fullname="Nat Sakimura"><organization>Nomura Research Institute</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>nat@sakimura.org</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="D." surname="Tonge" fullname="Dave Tonge"><organization>Moneyhub Financial Technology</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>dave@tonge.org</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2019" month="September" day="10"></date>
<area>Security</area>
<workgroup>Web Authorization Protocol</workgroup>
<keyword>security</keyword>
<keyword>oauth2</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>This document defines the pushed authorization request endpoint, which allows
clients to push the payload of an OAuth 2.0 authorization request to the
authorization server via a direct request and provides them
wih a request URI that is used as reference to the data in a subsequent authorization request.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="Introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>In OAuth <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> authorization request parameters are typically sent as URI query
parameters via redirection in the user-agent. This is simple but also yields challenges:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>There is no cryptographical integrity and authenticity protection, i.e. the request can be modified on its way throught the user agent and attackers can impersonate legitimate clients.</t>
</li>
<li><t>There is no mechanism to ensure confidentiality of the request parameters.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Authorization request URLs can become quite big, especially in scenarios requiring fine-grain authorization data.</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>JWT Secured Authorization Request (JAR) <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq"></xref> provides solutions for those challenges by allowing OAuth clients
to wrap authorization request parameters in a signed, and optionally encrypted, JSON Web Token
(JWT), the so-called &quot;request object&quot;.</t>
<t>In order to cope with the size restrictions, JAR introduces the <tt>request_uri</tt>
parameter that allows clients to send a reference to a request object
instead of the request object itself.</t>
<t>This document complements JAR by providing an interoperable way to push
the payload of a request object directly to the AS in exchange for a <tt>request_uri</tt>.</t>
<t>It also allows for clients to push the form encoded authorization request parameters to the AS in order to<br />
exchange them for a request URI that the client can use in a subsequent authorization request.</t>
<t>For example, the following authorization request,</t>

<artwork>  GET /authorize?response_type=code
   &amp;client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&amp;state=af0ifjsldkj
   &amp;redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fclient.example.org%2Fcb HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
       
</artwork>
<t>could be pushed directly to the AS by the client as follows,</t>

<artwork>  POST /as/par HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
  Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
  Authorization: Basic czZCaGRSa3F0Mzo3RmpmcDBaQnIxS3REUmJuZlZkbUl3

  response_type=code
  &amp;client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&amp;state=af0ifjsldkj
  &amp;redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fclient.example.org%2Fcb
</artwork>
<t>The AS responds with a request URI,</t>

<artwork>  HTTP/1.1 201 Created
  Cache-Control: no-cache, no-store
  Content-Type: application/json
    
  {

    &quot;request_uri&quot;:
       &quot;urn:example:bwc4JK-ESC0w8acc191e-Y1LTC2&quot;,
    &quot;expires_in&quot;: 90
  }
</artwork>
<t>which is used by the client in the subsequent authorization request as follows,</t>

<artwork>  GET /authorize?request_uri=
    urn%3Aexample%3Abwc4JK-ESC0w8acc191e-Y1LTC2 HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
</artwork>
<t>The pushed authorization request endpoint thus fosters OAuth security by providing all clients a simple means for an integrity protected authorization request, but it also allows clients requiring an even higher security level, especially cryptographically confirmed non-repudiation, to explicitly adopt JWT-based request objects.</t>

<section anchor="conventions-and-terminology"><name>Conventions and Terminology</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL
NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;,
&quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as
described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only when, they
appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
<t>This specification uses the terms &quot;access token&quot;, &quot;refresh token&quot;,
&quot;authorization server&quot;, &quot;resource server&quot;, &quot;authorization endpoint&quot;,
&quot;authorization request&quot;, &quot;authorization response&quot;, &quot;token endpoint&quot;,
&quot;grant type&quot;, &quot;access token request&quot;, &quot;access token response&quot;, and
&quot;client&quot; defined by The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="pushed-authorization-request-endpoint"><name>Pushed Authorization Request Endpoint</name>
<t>The pushed authorization request endpoint shall be a RESTful API at the authorization server that accepts <tt>x-www-form-urlencoded</tt> POST requests.</t>
<t>The endpoint accepts the parameters defined in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> for the authorization endpoint as well as all applicable extensions defined for the authorization endpoint. Some examples of such extensions include PKCE <xref target="RFC7636"></xref>, Resource Indicators <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-resource-indicators"></xref>, and OpenID Connect <xref target="OIDC"></xref>.</t>
<t>The rules for client authentication as defined in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> for token endpoint requests, including the applicable authentication methods, apply for the pushed authorization request endpoint as well. If applicable, the <tt>token_endpoint_auth_method</tt> client metadata parameter indicates the registered authentication method for the client to use when making direct requests to the authorization server, including requests to the pushed authorization endpoint.</t>
<t>Note that there's some potential ambiguity around the appropriate audience
value to use when JWT client assertion based authentication is employed. To address that ambiguity the issuer identifier URL of the AS according to <xref target="RFC8414"></xref> SHOULD be used as the value of the audience. In order to facilitate interoperability the AS MUST accept its issuer identifier, token endpoint URL, or pushed authorization request endpoint URL as values that identify it as an intended audience.</t>

<section anchor="request"><name>Request</name>
<t>A client can send all the parameters that usually comprise an authorization request to the pushed authorization request endpoint. A basic parameter set will typically include:</t>

<ul>
<li><t><tt>response_type</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>redirect_uri</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>scope</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>state</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>code_challenge</tt><br />
</t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>code_challenge_method</tt><br />
</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>Depending on client type and authentication method, the request might also include the <tt>client_id</tt> parameter. The <tt>request_uri</tt> authorization request parameter MUST NOT be provided.</t>
<t>The client adds the parameters in <tt>x-www-form-urlencoded</tt> format with a character encoding of UTF-8 as described in Appendix B of <xref target="RFC6749"></xref> to the body of a HTTP POST request. If applicable, the client also adds client credentials to the request header or the request body using the same rules as for token endpoint requests.</t>
<t>This is illustrated by the following example</t>

<artwork>  POST /as/par HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
  Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
  Authorization: Basic czZCaGRSa3F0Mzo3RmpmcDBaQnIxS3REUmJuZlZkbUl3

  response_type=code&amp;
  state=af0ifjsldkj&amp;
  client_id=s6BhdRkqt3&amp;
  redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fclient.example.org%2Fcb&amp;
  code_challenge=K2-ltc83acc4h0c9w6ESC_rEMTJ3bww-uCHaoeK1t8U&amp;
  code_challenge_method=S256&amp;
  scope=ais
</artwork>
<t>The AS MUST process the request as follows:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>The AS MUST authenticate the client in same way as at the token endpoint.</t>
</li>
<li><t>The AS MUST validate the request the same way as at the authorization endpoint. For example, the authorization server checks whether the redirect URI matches one of the redirect URIs configured for the <tt>client_id</tt>. It may also check whether the client is authorized for the <tt>scope</tt> for which it is requesting access. This validation allows the authorization server to refuse unauthorized or fraudulent requests early.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="successful-response"><name>Successful Response</name>
<t>If the verification is successful, the server shall generate a request URI and return a JSON payload that contains <tt>request_uri</tt> and <tt>expires_in</tt> members at the top level with <tt>201 Created</tt> HTTP response code.</t>

<ul>
<li><t><tt>request_uri</tt> : The request URI corresponding to the authorization request posted. This URI is used as reference to the respective request data in the subsequent authorization request only. The way the authorization process obtains the authorization request data is at the discretion of the authorization server and out of scope of this specification. There is no need to make the authorization request data available to other parties via this URI.</t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>expires_in</tt> : A JSON number that represents the lifetime of the request URI in seconds. The request URI lifetime is at the discretion of the AS.</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>The <tt>request_uri</tt> value MUST be generated using a cryptographically strong pseudorandom algorithm such that it is computationally infeasible to predict or guess a valid value.</t>
<t>The <tt>request URI</tt> MUST be bound to the <tt>client_id</tt> of the client that posted the authorization request.</t>
<t>Since the request URI can be replayed, its lifetime SHOULD be short and preferably limited to one-time use.</t>
<t>The following is an example of such a response:</t>

<artwork>  HTTP/1.1 201 Created
  Date: Tue, 2 May 2017 15:22:31 GMT
  Content-Type: application/json

  {
    &quot;request_uri&quot;: &quot;urn:example:bwc4JK-ESC0w8acc191e-Y1LTC2&quot;,
    &quot;expires_in&quot;: 3600
  }
</artwork>
</section>

<section anchor="error_response"><name>Error Response</name>

<section anchor="error-responses"><name>Error responses</name>

<section anchor="authentication-required"><name>Authentication required</name>
<t>If the client authentication fails, the authorization server shall return <tt>401 Unauthorized</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="authorization-required"><name>Authorization required</name>
<t>If the client is not authorized to perform the authorization request it wanted to post, the authorization server shall return <tt>403 Forbidden</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="invalid-request"><name>Invalid request</name>
<t>If the request object received is invalid, the authorization server shall return <tt>400 Bad Request</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="method-not-allowed"><name>Method not allowed</name>
<t>If the request did not use POST, the authorization server shall return <tt>405 Method Not Allowed</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="request-entity-too-large"><name>Request entity too large</name>
<t>If the request size was beyond the upper bound that the authorization server allows, the authorization server shall return a <tt>413 Request Entity Too Large</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="too-many-requests"><name>Too many requests</name>
<t>If the request from the client per a time period goes beyond the number the authorization server allows, the authorization server shall return a <tt>429 Too Many Requests</tt> HTTP error response.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="request-parameter"><name>&quot;request&quot; Parameter</name>
<t>Clients MAY use the <tt>request</tt> parameter as defined in JAR to push a request object to the AS.  This will allow both the Client and the AS to store the request object for the purposes of cryptographically confirmed non-repudiation.</t>
<t>The rules for signing and encryption of the request object as defined in JAR <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq"></xref> apply.</t>
<t>Clients MUST NOT combine other authorization request parameters with the <tt>request</tt> parameter at the pushed authorization request endpoint.</t>
<t>The following is an example of a request using a signed request object. The client is authenticated using its client secret <tt>BASIC</tt> authorization:</t>

<artwork>  POST /as/par HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
  Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
  Authorization: Basic czZCaGRSa3F0Mzo3RmpmcDBaQnIxS3REUmJuZlZkbUl3

  request=eyJraWQiOiJrMmJkYyIsImFsZyI6IlJTMjU2In0.eyJpc3MiOiJzNkJoZ
  FJrcXQzIiwiYXVkIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9zZXJ2ZXIuZXhhbXBsZS5jb20iLCJyZXNwb2
  5zZV90eXBlIjoiY29kZSIsImNsaWVudF9pZCI6InM2QmhkUmtxdDMiLCJyZWRpcmV
  jdF91cmkiOiJodHRwczovL2NsaWVudC5leGFtcGxlLm9yZy9jYiIsInNjb3BlIjoi
  YWlzIiwic3RhdGUiOiJhZjBpZmpzbGRraiIsImNvZGVfY2hhbGxlbmdlIjoiSzItb
  HRjODNhY2M0aDBjOXc2RVNDX3JFTVRKM2J3dy11Q0hhb2VLMXQ4VSIsImNvZGVfY2
  hhbGxlbmdlX21ldGhvZCI6IlMyNTYifQ.O49ffUxRPdNkN3TRYDvbEYVr1CeAL64u
  W4FenV3n9WlaFIRHeFblzv-wlEtMm8-tusGxeE9z3ek6FxkhvvLEqEpjthXnyXqqy
  Jfq3k9GSf5ay74ml_0D6lHE1hy-kVWg7SgoPQ-GB1xQ9NRhF3EKS7UZIrUHbFUCF0
  MsRLbmtIvaLYbQH_Ef3UkDLOGiU7exhVFTPeyQUTM9FF-u3K-zX-FO05_brYxNGLh
  VkO1G8MjqQnn2HpAzlBd5179WTzTYhKmhTiwzH-qlBBI_9GLJmE3KOipko9TfSpa2
  6H4JOlMyfZFl0PCJwkByS0xZFJ2sTo3Gkk488RQohhgt1I0onw
</artwork>
<t>The AS needs to take the following steps beyond the processing rules defined in <xref target="request"></xref>:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>If applicable, the AS decrypts the request object as specified in JAR <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq"></xref>, section 6.1.</t>
</li>
<li><t>The AS validates the request object signature as specified in JAR <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq"></xref>, section 6.2.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If the client is a confidential client, the authorization server MUST check whether the authenticated <tt>client_id</tt> matches the <tt>client_id</tt> claim in the request object. If they do not match, the authorization server MUST refuse to process the request. It is at the authorization server's discretion to require the <tt>iss</tt> claim to match the <tt>client_id</tt> as well.</t>
</li>
</ol>

<section anchor="error-responses-for-request-object"><name>Error responses for Request Object</name>
<t>This section gives the error responses that go beyond the basic <xref target="error_response"></xref>.</t>

<section anchor="authentication-required-1"><name>Authentication Required</name>
<t>If the signature validation fails, the authorization server shall return <tt>401 Unauthorized</tt> HTTP error response. The same applies if the <tt>client_id</tt> or, if applicable, the <tt>iss</tt> claims in the request object do not match the authenticated <tt>client_id</tt>.</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="authorization-request"><name>Authorization Request</name>
<t>The client uses the <tt>request_uri</tt> value as returned by the authorization server as authorization request parameter <tt>request_uri</tt>.</t>

<artwork>  GET /authorize?request_uri=
    urn%3Aexample%3Abwc4JK-ESC0w8acc191e-Y1LTC2 HTTP/1.1
  Host: as.example.com
</artwork>
<t>Clients are encouraged to use the request URI as the only parameter in order to use the integrity and authenticity provided by the pushed authorization request.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="authorization-server-metadata"><name>Authorization Server Metadata</name>
<t>If the authorization server has a pushed authorization request endpoint, it SHOULD include the following OAuth/OpenID Provider Metadata parameter in discovery responses:</t>
<t><tt>pushed_authorization_request_endpoint</tt> : The URL of the pushed authorization request endpoint at which the client can exchange the authorization request parameters or request object for a request URI.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations"><name>Security Considerations</name>

<section anchor="request-uri-guessing"><name>Request URI Guessing</name>
<t>An attacker could attempt to guess and replay a valid request URI value and
try to impersonate the respective client. The AS MUST consider the considerations
given in JAR <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq"></xref>, section 10.2, clause d on request URI entropy.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="request-uri-replay"><name>Request URI Replay</name>
<t>An attacker could replay a request URI captured from a legitimate authorization request. In order to cope with such attacks, the AS SHOULD make the request URIs one-time use.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="client-policy-change"><name>Client Policy Change</name>
<t>The client policy might change between the lodging of the authorization request parameters or request object and the
authorization request using a particular request object. It is therefore recommended that the AS checks the authorization request parameters against the client policy when processing the authorization request.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements"><name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>This specification is based on the work towards <eref target="https://bitbucket.org/openid/fapi/src/master/Financial_API_Pushed_Request_Object.md">Pushed Request Objects</eref>
conducted at the Financial Grade API working group at the OpenID Foundation. We would would like to thank the members of this WG for their valuable contributions.</t>
<t>We would like to thank Filip Skokan for his valuable feedback on this draft.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana_considerations"><name>IANA Considerations</name>
<t>...</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8414.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-jwsreq.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7636.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-resource-indicators.xml"/>
<reference anchor="OIDC" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
  <front>
    <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0 incorporating errata set 1</title>
    <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
      <organization>NRI</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization>Ping Identity</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mike Jones" initials="M." surname="Jones">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
      <organization>Google</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" month="Nov" day="8"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>

<section anchor="document-history"><name>Document History</name>
<t>[[ To be removed from the final specification ]]</t>
<t>-00</t>

<ul>
<li><t>first draft</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
