<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="fapi-2_0-00" submissionType="IETF" category="std" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="fapi-evolution">FAPI 2.0 Baseline Profile</title><seriesInfo value="fapi-2_0-00" status="standard" name="Internet-Draft"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="D." surname="Fett" fullname="Daniel Fett"><organization>yes.com</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>mail@danielfett.de</email>
</address></author>
<date/>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>connect</workgroup>
<keyword>security</keyword>
<keyword>openid</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>OIDF FAPI 2.0 is an API security profile based on the OAuth 2.0
Authorization Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>

<section anchor="warning"><name>Warning</name>
<t>This document is not an OIDF International Standard. It is distributed
for review and comment. It is subject to change without notice and may
not be referred to as an International Standard.</t>
<t>Recipients of this draft are invited to submit, with their comments,
notification of any relevant patent rights of which they are aware and
to provide supporting documentation.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="copyright-notice-license"><name>Copyright notice &amp; license</name>
<t>The OpenID Foundation (OIDF) grants to any Contributor, developer,
implementer, or other interested party a non-exclusive, royalty free,
worldwide copyright license to reproduce, prepare derivative works
from, distribute, perform and display, this Implementers Draft or
Final Specification solely for the purposes of (i) developing
specifications, and (ii) implementing Implementers Drafts and Final
Specifications based on such documents, provided that attribution be
made to the OIDF as the source of the material, but that such
attribution does not indicate an endorsement by the OIDF.</t>
<t>The technology described in this specification was made available from
contributions from various sources, including members of the OpenID
Foundation and others. Although the OpenID Foundation has taken steps
to help ensure that the technology is available for distribution, it
takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual
property or other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the
implementation or use of the technology described in this
specification or the extent to which any license under such rights
might or might not be available; neither does it represent that it has
made any independent effort to identify any such rights. The OpenID
Foundation and the contributors to this specification make no (and
hereby expressly disclaim any) warranties (express, implied, or
otherwise), including implied warranties of merchantability,
non-infringement, fitness for a particular purpose, or title, related
to this specification, and the entire risk as to implementing this
specification is assumed by the implementer. The OpenID Intellectual
Property Rights policy requires contributors to offer a patent promise
not to assert certain patent claims against other contributors and
against implementers. The OpenID Foundation invites any interested
party to bring to its attention any copyrights, patents, patent
applications, or other proprietary rights that may cover technology
that may be required to practice this specification.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="notational-conventions"><name>Notational Conventions</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and
&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC
2119 [RFC2119].</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="baseline-profile"><name>Baseline Profile</name>
<t>OIDF FAPI is an API security profile based on the OAuth 2.0
Authorization Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref>. It aims to reach the security
goals laid out in the [Attacker Model].</t>

<section anchor="network-layer-protections"><name>Network Layer Protections</name>
<t>To protect against network attackers, clients, authorization servers,
and resource servers MUST only offer TLS protected endpoints and MUST
establish connections to other servers using TLS. TLS connections MUST
be set up to use TLS version 1.2 or later and follow <xref target="RFC7525"></xref>.</t>
<t>Endpoints for the use by web browsers MUST use methods to ensure that
connections cannot be downgraded using TLS Stripping attacks. A
preloaded <xref target="preload"></xref> HTTP Strict Transport Security policy <xref target="RFC6797"></xref>
can be used for this purpose. Some top-level domains, like .bank and
.insurance, have set such a policy and therefore protect all
second-level domains below them.</t>
<t>For a comprehensive protection against network attackers, all
endpoints SHOULD additionally use DNSSEC to protect against DNS
spoofing attacks that can lead to the issuance of rogue
domain-validated TLS certificates. Note: Even if an endpoint uses only
organization validated (OV) or extended validation (EV) TLS
certificates, rogue domain-validated certificates can be used to
impersonate the endpoints and conduct man-in-the-middle attacks.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="profile"><name>Profile</name>
<t>In the following, a profile of the following technologies is defined:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework <xref target="RFC6749"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Bearer Tokens <xref target="RFC6750"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 PKCE <xref target="RFC7636"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Mutual-TLS Client Authentication <xref target="RFC8705"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Pushed Authorization Requests (PAR) <xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-par"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Rich Authorization Requests (RAR) <xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-rar"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OAuth 2.0 Authorization Server Metadata <xref target="RFC8414"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>OpenID Connect Core 1.0 incorporating errata set 1 <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
</ul>

<section anchor="requirements-for-authorization-servers"><name>Requirements for Authorization Servers</name>
<t>Authorization servers</t>

<ol>
<li><t>MUST adhere to <xref target="I-D.ietf-oauth-security-topics"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support the authorization code grant described in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support client-authenticated pushed authorization requests
according to <xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-par"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST NOT support authorization requests sent without
<xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-par"></xref> or authorization request parameters
sent outside of the PAR request, except for
<tt>request_uri</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST NOT support pushed authorization requests without client authentication</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support rich authorization requests according to <xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-rar"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support confidential clients as defined in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support and sender-constraining of access tokens using Mutual TLS as described in <xref target="RFC8705"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST authenticate clients using one of the following methods:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>Mutual TLS for OAuth Client Authentication as specified in section 2 of <xref target="RFC8705"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>private_key_jwt</tt> as specified in section 9 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
</ol></li>
<li><t>MUST require PKCE <xref target="RFC7636"></xref> with <tt>S256</tt> as the code challenge method</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST only issue authorization codes, access tokens, and refresh tokens that are sender-constrained</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST require the <tt>redirect_uri</tt> parameter in authorization requests and evaluate only this parameter to ensure authenticity and integrity of the redirect URI</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST require that redirect URIs use the <tt>https</tt> scheme</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST verify, if possible, that the authorization code (section 1.3.1 of [RFC6749]) has not been previously used</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST provide a means for resource servers to verify the validity, integrity, sender-constraining, scope (incl. <tt>authorization_details</tt>), expiration and revocation status of an access token, either by providing an introspection endpoint <xref target="RFC7662"></xref>, by exposing signature verification keys, or by deployment-specific means.</t>
</li>
</ol>
<t><strong>NOTE</strong>: If replay identification of the authorization code is not possible, it is desirable to set the validity period of the authorization code to one minute or a suitable short period of time. The validity period may act as a cache control indicator of when to clear the authorization code cache if one is used.</t>

<section anchor="returning-authenticated-user-s-identifier"><name>Returning Authenticated User's Identifier</name>
<t>If it is desired to provide the authenticated user's identifier to the client in the token response, the authorization server:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>MUST support the authentication request as in Section 3.1.2.1 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST perform the authentication request verification as in Section 3.1.2.2 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST authenticate the user as in Section 3.1.2.2 and 3.1.2.3 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST provide the authentication response as in Section 3.1.2.4 and 3.1.2.5 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref> depending on the outcome of the authentication</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST perform the token request verification as in Section 3.1.3.2 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST issue an ID Token in the token response when <tt>openid</tt> was included in the requested <tt>scope</tt>
as in Section 3.1.3.3 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref> with its <tt>sub</tt> value corresponding to the authenticated user
and optional <tt>acr</tt> value in ID Token.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-for-clients"><name>Requirements for Clients</name>
<t>Clients</t>

<ol>
<li><t>MUST use the authorization code grant described in <xref target="RFC6749"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST use pushed authorization requests according to
<xref target="I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-par"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST use sender-constrained access
tokens using Mutual TLS as described in <xref target="RFC8705"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST support client authentication using one of the following methods:</t>

<ol>
<li><t>Mutual TLS for OAuth Client Authentication as specified in section 2 of <xref target="RFC8705"></xref></t>
</li>
<li><t><tt>private_key_jwt</tt> as specified in section 9 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref></t>
</li>
</ol></li>
<li><t>MUST use PKCE <xref target="RFC7636"></xref> with <tt>S256</tt> as the code challenge method</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST send access tokens in the HTTP header as in Section 2.1 of
OAuth 2.0 Bearer Token Usage [RFC6750]</t>
</li>
<li><t>MAY send the last time the customer logged into the client in the
<tt>x-fapi-auth-date</tt> header where the value is supplied as a
HTTP-date as in section 7.1.1.1 of [RFC7231], e.g.,
<tt>x-fapi-auth-date: Tue, 11 Sep 2012 19:43:31 GMT</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t>MAY send the customer’s IP address if this data is available in
the <tt>x-fapi-customer-ip-address</tt> header, e.g.,
<tt>x-fapi-customer-ip-address: 198.51.100.119</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t>MAY send the <tt>x-fapi-interaction-id</tt> request header whose value is
a [RFC4122] UUID to the server to help correlate log entries
between client and server, e.g., <tt>x-fapi-interaction-id:
c770aef3-6784-41f7-8e0e-ff5f97bddb3a</tt></t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="requirements-for-resource-servers"><name>Requirements for Resource Servers</name>
<t>The FAPI 2.0 endpoints are OAuth 2.0 protected resource endpoints that return protected information for the resource owner associated with the submitted access token.</t>
<t>Resource servers with the FAPI endpoints</t>

<ol>
<li><t>MUST accept access tokens in the HTTP header as in Section 2.1 of OAuth 2.0 Bearer Token Usage [RFC6750]</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST not accept access tokens in the query parameters stated in Section 2.3 of OAuth 2.0 Bearer Token Usage [RFC6750]</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST verify the validity, integrity, expiration and revocation status of access tokens</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST verify that the scope (incl. <tt>authorization_details</tt>) of the access token authorizes the access to the resource it is representing</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST verify sender-constraining for access tokens</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST identify the associated entity to the access token</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST only return the resource identified by the combination of the entity implicit in the access and the granted scope and otherwise return errors as in section 3.1 of [RFC6750]</t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST set the response header <tt>x-fapi-interaction-id</tt> to the value received from the corresponding fapi client request header or to a [RFC4122] UUID value if the request header was not provided to track the interaction, e.g., <tt>x-fapi-interaction-id: c770aef3-6784-41f7-8e0e-ff5f97bddb3a</tt></t>
</li>
<li><t>MUST log the value of <tt>x-fapi-interaction-id</tt> in the log entry</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="cryptography-and-secrets"><name>Cryptography and Secrets</name>

<ol>
<li><t>RSA keys MUST have a minimum length of 2048 bits.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Elliptic curve keys MUST have a minimum length of 160 bits.</t>
</li>
<li><t>authorization servers MUST provide a client secret that adheres to the requirements in section 16.19 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref> if a symmetric key is used</t>
</li>
<li><t>Access tokens MUST be non-guessable with a minimum of 128 bits of entropy where the probability of an attacker guessing the generated token is less than or equal to 2^(-160) as per [RFC6749] section 10.10.</t>
</li>
</ol>
</section>

<section anchor="differences-to-fapi-1-0"><name>Differences to FAPI 1.0</name>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="left">FAPI 1.0 Read/Write</th>
<th align="left">FAPI 2.0</th>
<th align="left">Reasons</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left">JAR, JARM</td>
<td align="left">PAR</td>
<td align="left">integrity protection and compatibility improvements for authorization requests; only code in response</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">RAR</td>
<td align="left">support complex and structured information about authorizations</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">MUST adhere to Security BCP</td>
<td align="left"></td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>s_hash</tt></td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">state integrity is protected by PAR; protection provided by state is now provided by PKCE</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">pre-registered redirect URIs</td>
<td align="left">redirect URIs in PAR</td>
<td align="left">pre-registration is not required with client authentication and PAR</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">response types <tt>code id_token</tt> or <tt>code</tt></td>
<td align="left">response type <tt>code</tt></td>
<td align="left">improve security: no ID token in front-channel; not needed</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">ID Token as detached signature</td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">ID token does not need to serve as a detached signature</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left">signed and encrypted ID Tokens</td>
<td align="left">signing and encryption not required</td>
<td align="left">ID Tokens only exchanged in back channel</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td align="left"><tt>exp</tt> claim in request object</td>
<td align="left">-</td>
<td align="left">?</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></section>

<section anchor="open-questions"><name>Open questions:</name>

<ul>
<li><t>disallow scopes? if yes, use RAR transport for openid claim</t>
</li>
<li><t>Response types? ID Token in front channel?</t>
</li>
<li><t></t>
</li>
<li><t>lifetime for request objects?</t>
</li>
<li><t>(to be moved to grant management):</t>

<ul>
<li><t>shall require explicit consent by the user to authorize the requested scope if it has not been previously authorized;</t>
</li>
<li><t>should clearly identify long-term grants to the user during authorization as in 16.18 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref>; and</t>
</li>
<li><t>should provide a mechanism for the end-user to revoke access tokens and refresh tokens granted to a client as in 16.18 of <xref target="OpenID"></xref>.</t>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>(relevance/meaning unclear):</t>

<ul>
<li><t>shall return token responses that conform to section 4.1.4 of [RFC6749];</t>
</li>
<li><t>shall return an invalid_client error as defined in 5.2 of [RFC6749] when mis-matched client identifiers were provided through the client authentication methods that permits sending the client identifier in more than one way;</t>
</li>
<li><t>The Financial-grade API server may limit the scopes for the purpose of not implementing certain APIs.</t>
</li>
<li><t>(RS) MUST encode the response in UTF-8 if applicable;</t>
</li>
<li><t>(RS) MUST send the <tt>Content-type</tt> HTTP header <tt>Content-Type: application/json; charset=UTF-8</tt> if applicable;</t>
</li>
<li><t>(RS) MUST send the server date in HTTP Date header as in section 7.1.1.2 of [RFC7231];</t>
</li>
<li><t>(RS) SHOULD support CORS for JS clients</t>
</li>
</ul></li>
<li><t>Check Sections 7/8</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7525.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7636.xml"/>
<reference anchor="OpenID" target="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-core-1_0.html">
  <front>
    <title>OpenID Connect Core 1.0 incorporating errata set 1</title>
    <author fullname="Nat Sakimura" initials="N." surname="Sakimura">
      <organization>NRI</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization>Ping Identity</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mike Jones" initials="M." surname="Jones">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Breno de Medeiros" initials="B." surname="de Medeiros">
      <organization>Google</organization>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Chuck Mortimore" initials="C." surname="Mortimore">
      <organization>Salesforce</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" month="Nov" day="8"></date>
  </front>
</reference>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7662.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6749.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6797.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6750.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8705.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8414.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-rar.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.lodderstedt-oauth-par.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-security-topics.xml"/>
<reference anchor="preload" target="https://hstspreload.org/">
  <front>
    <title>HSTS Preload List Submission</title>
    <author fullname="Anonymous">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date></date>
  </front>
</reference>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
